Guide to the Hendrik Willem van Loon papers, 1884-1972.
Van Loon, Hendrick Willem papers,
- Series II. Family correspondence
  - Subseries IIc. Correspondence To And From Hendrik Willem van Loon
    - Frances Goodrich, n.d., miscellaneous (includes small drawings and undated notes) (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Ben Huebsch, 1913-1935 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Ben Huebsch, 1936-1943, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Hattie-Bell Johnston, 1927-1943 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Juliana, Queen of the Netherlands, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Juliana, Queen of the Netherlands, 1941-1944 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Mary Powell/ Charles Kingsford-Smith, 1930-1933 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Marvin Lowenthal, 1936-1939 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Marvin Lowenthal, 1940-1944 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Thomas Mann, 1936-1944 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1938 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1939 (Box 14, Folder 3-5)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1940 (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1941 (Box 14, Folder 9-10)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1942 (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1943 (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
    - Elizabeth Marion (Saunders), 1944 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Henri Mayer, 1924 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Henri Mayer, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Henri Mayer, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Henri Mayer, 1927-1928 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Henri Mayer, 1930-1931 (includes one two-page newspaper article) (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Henri Mayer, 1932 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Henri Mayer, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Henri Mayer, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Henri Mayer, 1935 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Henri Mayer, 1936 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Henri Mayer, 1937 Jan. -Aug. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Henri Mayer, 1937 Sept. -Dec. (includes one fragment from Mayer) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Henri Mayer, 1938 Jan. -July (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Henri Mayer, 1938 Aug. -Dec. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Henri Mayer, 1939 Jan. -June (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Henri Mayer, 1939 July-Dec. (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Henri Mayer, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Henri Mayer, 1941 (includes one letter from Mayer to Jimmie, 1945) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Joost A.M. Meerloo (MD), 1940-1944 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Charles Recht, 1919-1928, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1941 July-Nov. (includes letter from Pierre van Paassen) (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1942 Jan. -June (letter from Ries) (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1942 July-Dec. (letter from Ries) (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1943 Jan. -June (includes typescript copy of an introduction to Van Loon's Lives-A History of the World Written for the Benefit of Those Who Came Back) (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1943 July-Dec. (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, 1944 (includes several letters to Ries from Jimmie after Hendrik's death) (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Dr. L. Arthur Ries, n. d. (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt, 1932-1947 letters from E.R. (several to Jimmie after Hendrik's death) originals (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1932-1936 letters from F.D.R., originals (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1939-1944 (includes several letters to Jimmie after Hendrik's death, and one letter from Mrs. James Roosevelt) (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, letters to F.D.R. (originals) (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1931-1936 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1937 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1938 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1939 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1940 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1941 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - FROM: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes photocopies), 1942-1944 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1933-1935 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1936-1937 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1938 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1939 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1940 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - TO: Franklin D. Roosevelt (includes letter and typescript copies), 1940-1944 (letters from family after Hendrik's death) (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - George Saville, 1929-1934 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - George Saville, 1935-1942, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Rene Scudamore, 1928-1930 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Rene Scudamore, 1931-1932 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Rene Scudamore, 1937 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Rene Scudamore, 1938 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Rene Scudamore, 1939-1943 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Rene Scudamore, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1928 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1929 Jan. -Aug. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1929 Sept. -Dec. (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1930 Jan. -June (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1930 July-Oct. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1931-1934 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1935, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Erik "Din" Smit (photocopies), 1939 letters from Jimmie 1945-1952 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Mary Sullivan (originals), 1926-1935 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Mary Sullivan (originals), 1936-1939 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Mary Sullivan (originals), 1940-1943 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Mary Sullivan (originals), n.d. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Lucie Van Tal, 1927-1943 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Andrew D. White, 1904-1917 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Series III. Major correspondents
  Major correspondents include those individuals who were considered important personalities in the 1900's-1940's, with whom Hendrik wrote irregularly (less than ten letters). This material is listed alphabetically and includes number of letters and inclusive dates. Also included in this series are draft copies of correspondence and microfilmed correspondence.
  - Subseries IIIa. Alphabetically Arranged Letters to van Loon
    - Dr. Frank Ezra Adcock, Feb. 12, 1921, 1 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Winthrop Ames, June 23, 1921, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Peggy Bacon, Mar. 8, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Ernest Sutherland Bates, July 15, 1927, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Ludwig Bemelmans, 1941, n.d., 3 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Count Bernadotte, Aug. 3, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Francis Biddle, Nov. 28, 1942, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Boni and Liveright Inc. (several letters from van Loon), 1921-1923, 4 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Rita and Stephan Bonsai, 1934-1942, 6 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - J.A. Bouman, Christmas Eve 1943, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Margaret Bourke-White (Caldwell), n. d., 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Louis Bromfield, 1943, n.d., 2 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Van Wyck Brooks (includes several postcards), 1936-1943, n.d., 8 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - William Jennings Bryan, May 28, 1915, 1 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Pearl S. Buck Mar. 7 & Apr. 11,, 1933, Nov. 16, 1938, 3 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Willa S. Cather, Jan. 1, 1943, 1 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Aaron Copland, Oct. 30, ?, 1 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Archibald Cary Coolidge, June 6, 1916, 1 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Wilbur L. Cross, 1938, 2 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Charles William Dabney, To: 1901, 1902 From: 1943, 3 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Walter Damrosch, 1935-1942, 6 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Jay N. Darling, 1942, 3 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Harding Davis' (Richard, Hope, Bessie), 1902-1903, 1919, 1929-1930, 7 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Douglas Z. Doty, 1914-1915, 3 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Max Eastman, Apr. 20, 1942, 1 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Walter D. Edmonds, September 1, 1936, 1 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Walter Prichard Eaton, 1925, 2 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Albert Ehrenstein (encl. bibliography of, 1943, 1 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Oscar Fabres his works), 1940-1942, 4 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Clifton (Kip) Fadiman, 1933-1943, 4 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Kirsten Flagstad, n. d., 3 (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Gilda Gray, 1943, 1 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - John Gunther, Nov. 22, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Francis Hackett, Signe Toksvig (Mrs. Hackett, 1941, 1943 ), 2 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Walter Hampden, Oct. 19, 1938, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Dr. Ernst Hanfstaengl, May 8, 1935, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Maurice Hanline, 1940-1941, 5 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Florence Harriman (Mrs. J. Borden Harriman), Oct. 7, 1941, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Sven Hedin, 1936, 1938, 2 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Josef Hofmann, Jan. 18, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Elliot Henry Holt, 1913, 1927, 2 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Herbert Hoover, 1940-1944, 9 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Harry L. Hopkins, 1938-1939, 3 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Roy W. Howard, Nov. 16, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Rupert Hughes, 1932, 2 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Cordell Hull, June 7, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Fanny Hurst, 1935-1940, 4 (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Hans Kindler, 1941 (?), 1 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Ten Klooster, 1938-1939, 2 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Charles Koch, July 7, 1943, 1 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Fritz Kreisler, 1920, 2 (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Fiorello LaGuardia, 1935-1943, 7 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Ring Lardner, Jan. 27, 1933, 1 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Sinclair Lewis, 1941, 1 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Kate Lofting, Dec. 17, 1928, 1 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Pauline Lord, June 21, 1927, 1 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Clare Boothe Luce, 1942, 1943, 2 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Emil Ludwig, 1932, 2 (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Archibald MacLeish, March 6, 1942, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Ludwig Marcuse, Jan. 31, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - W. S. Maugham, Oct. 18, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - William McFee, March 10, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Lauritz Melchior, Dec. 29, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Mrs. Wm. Brown Meloney, Jan. 17, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - H.L. Mencken, 1936, 1942, 2 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Paul E. More, 1912, 2 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Anne Morgan, 1933-1943, 6 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Arthur E. Morgan, July 28, 1921, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Herbert Morrison, July 1, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - William A. Neilson, Nov. 6, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Ruth Bryon Owen, 1935, 2 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - To: Arthur Pell, March 1931, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Gifford Pinchot, Oct. 2, 1915, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Lily K. Pons, 1941, n.d., 3 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - G.P. Putnam, Oct. 28, 1912, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Jean Renoir, Nov. 16, 1942, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Arthur Robinson, July 25, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Jules Romains, Dex. 4, 1940, 1 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Ruth St. Denis, 1939, 1941, 2 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - David Sarnoff, Sept. 8, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Max Schuster, 1937, 1943, 2 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Samuel Seabury, Nov. 4, 1937, 1 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Alexander P. de Seversky, May 8, 1942, 1 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Jean Sibelius Otis Skinner (one Cornelia Otis), 1938-1941 1932-1936, 36 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Vilhjalmur Stefansson, Feb. 16, 1935, 1 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - E.R. Stettinius, Jr., 1943, 2 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Melville E. Stone, 1905-1907, 1915, 4 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Rex Stout, 1942, 2 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Abbot and Gladys Thayer, 1913-1922, n.d., 8 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Dorothy Thompson, Nov. 21, 1939, 1 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Sybil Thorndike Signe Toksvig - see Francis Hackett, n. d., 3 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Alexandra L. Tolstoy, 1942-1943, 3 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Gene Tunney, 1934, 1 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Oswald Garrison Villard, 1929, 1938, 1942, 3 (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - H.A. Wallace, 1942, 2 (Box 17, Folder 25)
  - Subseries IIIb. Draft Copies of Correspondence
    - Draft copies dated 1906-1920 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Draft copies dated 1921-1923 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Draft copies dated 1924 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Draft copies dated 1925-1928 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Draft copies dated 1929-1931 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Draft copies dated 1932 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Draft copies dated 1933 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Draft copies dated 1934 (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
    - Draft copies dated 1935 (Box 18, Folder 10-11)
    - Draft copies dated 1936 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Draft copies dated 1937 (Box 18, Folder 13-14)
    - Draft copies dated 1938 (Box 18, Folder 15-18)
    - Draft copies dated 1939 (Box 18, Folder 19-21)
    - Draft copies dated 1940 (Box 18, Folder 22-25)
    - Draft copies dated 1941 (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
    - Draft copies dated 1942 (Box 19, Folder 5-9)
    - Draft copies dated 1943 (Box 19, Folder 10-12)
    - Draft copies dated 1944 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Subseries IIIc. Correspondence on Microfilm
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem van Loon to Andrew D. White, 1904-1917. (Reel 1)
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem van Loon to George Lincoln Burr, 1902-1921. (Reel 1)
    - Letters from files of Charles Recht pertaining to Hendrik Willem van Loon, 1919. (Reel 1)
    - Hendrik Willem van Loon correspondence with Ben Huebsch. (Reel 1)
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem and Helen Criswell van Loon to Erik "Din" Smith, 1928-1952. (Reel 1)
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem van Loon to H. Bauer (Library of Congress). (Reel 1)
    - Letters from Hendrik Willem van Loon to numerous unidentified people. (Reel 1)
    - Correspondence and other materials concerning Hendrik Willem van Loon in the papers of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. (Reel 2)
- Series IV. Manuscript material
  Manuscript material includes carbons, drafts, and typescripts for articles, books, broadcasts, lectures, serials, and Hendrik Willem van Loon's thesis. Book material is arranged alphabetically by title. Articles, broadcasts, lectures, serials, and the thesis are arranged separately in chronological order when possible. The letters N/A were used when no title was available.
  - Subseries IVa. Book Manuscripts
    - Adriaen Block, annotated typescript (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, carbon pages. 1-100 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, carbon (different version) p. 1-34 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, handwritten draft Chapter 1 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, Chapter 2 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, Chapters 3-4 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, Chapters 5-6 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Adventures and Escapes of Gustavus Vasa, Chapters 7-9 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - America, handwritten draft p. 1-46 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - America, handwritten and typescript draft, carbon list of chapter titles Chapters 1-5 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - America, Chapters 6-9 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - America, Chapters 10-14 (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - America, Chapters 15-18 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - America, Chapters 19-21 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - America, Chapter 22 (p. 268-317) (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - America, p. 318-348 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - America, p. 349-400 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - America, p. 401-443 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - America, p. 444-467 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - America, p. 468-518 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet, annotated carbon p. 1-45 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet, handwritten introduction, annotated typescript introduction typescript list of town names, carbon forward, typescript p. 1 (Box 20, Folder 22)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet, annotated typescript (Box 20, Folder 23)
    - Around the World with the Alphabet, handwritten draft (Box 20, Folder 24)
    - The Arts, "old version" annotated typescript p. 5-55 (Box 20, Folder 25)
    - The Arts, p. 56-104 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    - The Arts, p. 105-129 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    - The Arts, annotated typescript and handwritten draft p. 1-75 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - The Arts, p. 76-134 (Box 20, Folder 29)
    - The Arts, p. 135-236 (Box 20, Folder 30)
    - The Arts, p. 237-307c (Box 20, Folder 31)
    - The Arts, Chapter 19-p. 351 (Box 20, Folder 32)
    - The Arts, p. 352-397 (Box 20, Folder 33)
    - The Arts, p. 398-468 (Box 20, Folder 34)
    - The Arts, p. 469-541 (Box 20, Folder 35)
    - The Arts, p. 542-603 (Box 20, Folder 36)
    - The Arts, p. 604-669 (Box 20, Folder 37)
    - The Arts, p. 670-741 (Box 20, Folder 38)
    - The Arts, p. 742-793 (Box 20, Folder 39)
    - The Arts, p. 794-826b (Box 20, Folder 40)
    - The Arts, p. 826-912 (Box 20, Folder 41)
    - The Arts, printer's typescript copy with stamped numerals, contains book front, table of contents, and title pages (annotated) (Box 20, Folder 42)
    - The Arts, printer's typescript copy p. 1-70 (Box 20, Folder 43)
    - The Arts, p. 71-119 (Box 20, Folder 44)
    - The Arts, p. 120-164 (Box 20, Folder 45)
    - The Arts, p. 165-200 (Box 20, Folder 46)
    - The Arts, p. 201-249 (Box 20, Folder 47)
    - The Arts, p. 250-301 (Box 20, Folder 48)
    - The Arts, p. 302-364. (Box 20, Folder 49)
    - The Arts, p. 365-404 (Box 20, Folder 50)
    - The Arts, p. 405-469 (Box 20, Folder 51)
    - The Arts, p. 470-527 (Box 20, Folder 52)
    - The Arts, p. 528-627 (Box 20, Folder 53)
    - The Arts, p. 628-679 (Box 20, Folder 54)
    - The Arts, p. 680-721 (Box 20, Folder 55)
    - The Arts, p. 722-857 (Box 20, Folder 56)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, annotated typescript and carbon (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, typescript with editorial corrections p. 1-40 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, p. 41-103 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, handwritten and typescript draft p. 5-53 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, p. 54-95 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, p. 96-118 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, handwritten and typescript draft, title page and p. 1-52 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - An Elephant Up a Tree, handwritten and typescript draft p. 53-97 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Van Loon's Geography, typescript with editorial corrections. 1-50 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 51-107 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 108-167 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 168-214 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 215-284 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 285-349 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 350-417 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 418-494 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - Van Loon's Geography, p. 495-538 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Invasion, handwritten and typescript draft, introduction, foreword p. 1-75 (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Invasion, handwritten and typescript draft, introduction, foreword p. 1-55 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Invasion, p. 56-85 (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Invasion, p. 86-124 (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - Invasion, p. 125-180 (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Invasion, p. 181-216 (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, printed copy p. 1-16 (Box 21, Folder 24)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, p. 17-32 (Box 21, Folder 25)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, p. 33-48 (Box 21, Folder 26)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, p. 49-64 (Box 21, Folder 27)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, printed copy p. 65-80 (Box 21, Folder 28)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, p. 81-96, end paper (Box 21, Folder 29)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, handwritten draft p. 1-35 (Box 21, Folder 30)
    - The Last of the Troubadours, annotated typescript introduction p. 1-17 (Box 21, Folder 31)
    - The Life and Times of Johann Sebastian Bach, handwritten draft p. 1-39 (Box 21, Folder 32)
    - The Life and Times of Johann Sebastian Bach, p. 40-80 (Box 21, Folder 33)
    - The Life and Times of Johann Sebastian Bach, p. 81-125 (Box 21, Folder 34)
    - The Life and Times of Johann Sebastian Bach, P. 126-165 (Box 21, Folder 35)
    - The Life and Times of Johann Sebastian Bach, P. 166-epilogue, with several typescript and corrected pages (Box 21, Folder 36)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, annotated typescript with corrections p. 1-51 (Box 21, Folder 37)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, p. 52-107 (Box 21, Folder 38)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, frontispiece, dedication and other typescript corrected pages (Box 21, Folder 39)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, handwritten and typescript draft p. 1-39 (Box 21, Folder 40)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, p. 40-79 (Box 21, Folder 41)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, p. 80-110 (Box 21, Folder 42)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, p. 111-152, end papers (Box 21, Folder 43)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, handwritten draft p. 1-51 (Box 21, Folder 44)
    - The Life and Times of Simon Bolivar, movie idea of Bolivar (1940) treated by Stephen Sleisinger (with correspondence) (Box 21, Folder 45)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), handwritten and typescript draft with corrections p. 1-35 (Box 21, Folder 46)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 36-94 (Box 21, Folder 47)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 95-136c (Box 21, Folder 48)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 1-36 (Box 21, Folder 49)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 37-93 (Box 21, Folder 50)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 94-140 (Box 21, Folder 51)
    - Man the Miracle Maker (or Multiplex Man), p. 141-211 (Box 21, Folder 52)
    - Observations on the Mystery of Print, printed copy (Box 21, Folder 53)
    - Observations on the Mystery of Print, Galley Proof, with corrections and annotations (Box 21, Folder 54)
    - Observations on the Mystery of Print, typescript with corrections and annotations (Box 21, Folder 55)
    - Observations on the Mystery of Print, annotated carbon (Box 21, Folder 56)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, handwritten draft, typescript title page and other pages with annotations p. 1-42 (Box 21, Folder 57)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 43-100 (Box 21, Folder 58)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 101-159 (Box 21, Folder 59)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 160-210 (Box 21, Folder 60)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 211-258 (Box 21, Folder 61)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 259-302 (Box 21, Folder 62)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 303-397 (Box 21, Folder 63)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 398-444 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 445-500 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 226-300 (#'s change, see annotation) (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 301-349 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 350-391 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 392-448 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 449-491 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 492-556 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - R. V. R. Volume 1, p. 557-577, several extra pages (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Master Jan, annotated carbon with introduction (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - R. V. R. Volume 2, handwritten draft continued p. 578-620 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - R. V. R. Volume 2, p. 621-673 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - R. V. R. Volume 2, p. 674-730 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - R. V. R. Volume 2, p. 731-784 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - R. V. R. Volume 2, p. 785-842 (Box 22, Folder 15)